<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>An acte to enable the Kings Maiestie to make leases of lands, parcell of his highnesse dutchie of Cornewall, or annexed to the same</title>
            <title>Laws, etc.</title>
            <author>England and Wales.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1626</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 6 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 1 1-bit group-IV TIFF page image.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A22417</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 8837.5</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S3416</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">33149714</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 33149714</idno>
            <idno type="VID">28475</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A22417)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 28475)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1876:74)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>An acte to enable the Kings Maiestie to make leases of lands, parcell of his highnesse dutchie of Cornewall, or annexed to the same</title>
                  <title>Laws, etc.</title>
                  <author>England and Wales.</author>
                  <author>Charles I, King of England, 1600-1649.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>1 sheet ([1] p.).   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>By Bonham Norton and Iohn Bill, Printers  to the Kings most Excellent Maiestie,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Imprinted at London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>M.DC.XXVI [1626]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>At head of title: Anno primo Caroli Regis.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in: Society of Antiquaries.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Land tenure --  Law and legislation --  Great Britain --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Copyhold --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Great Britain --  History --  Charles I, 1625-1649.</term>
               <term>Broadsides --  London (England) --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2008-08</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2008-11</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-01</date>
            <label>Kayla Ondracek</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-01</date>
            <label>Kayla Ondracek</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:28475:1"/>
            <!-- PDF PAGE 6 -->
            <opener>
               <dateline>
                  <date>Anno primo Caroli Regis.</date>
               </dateline>
            </opener>
            <head>
               <g ref="char:leaf">❧</g> An Acte to enable the Kings Maieſtie to make Leaſes of Lands, parcell of his Highneſſe Dutchie of <hi>Cornewall,</hi> or annexed to the ſame.</head>
            <p>
               <hi>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>Hereas the King Our Soueraigne Lord, being in the life time of</hi> His Royall Father of bleſſed memory, ſeized of the ſaid Dukedome of <hi>Cornewall,</hi> did bargaine and contract for Leaſes and Eſtates to bee made of diuers Meſſuages, Lands, Tenements, and Hereditaments, parcell of the ſaid Dukedome of <hi>Cornewall,</hi> which Leaſes and Eſtates, His Maieſtie was enabled to haue made in His ſaid Fathers life time, by an Acte of Parliament made in the laſt Seſſion of Parliament, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tituled, An Acte to enable the moſt Excellent Prince <hi>Charles</hi> to make Leaſes of Lands, parcell of His Highneſſe Dutchy of <hi>Cornewall,</hi> or an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nexed to the ſame. And becauſe His Maieſtie, hauing receiued diuers Fines, and ſummes of Money, according to the ſaid Contracts, and hauing entred into Treatie with diuers others for like Eſtates, the finiſhing of which Contracts, and making the ſaid Lea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, was preuented by His Maieſties acceſſe to the Imperiall Crowne of this Realme, is graci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly pleaſed for the good of his poore Tenants of the ſaid Dutchy Lands, to proceed to the full accompliſhment of the Contracts, and Leaſes of the premiſſes.</p>
            <p>Bee it therefore enacted by our ſaid Soueraigne Lord the King, the Lords Spirituall and Temporall, and Commons in this preſent Parliament aſſembled, and by authority of this pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent Parliament, That all Leaſes to be made within the ſpace of three yeeres now next enſuing by our ſaid Soueraigne Lord the King, by letters Patents, Indentures, or other writings vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der His great Seale of England, or Seale of the Court of Exchequer, of any Mannors, Lands, Tenements, or Hereditaments, parcell of the poſſeſſions of the ſaid Dutchy of <hi>Cornewall,</hi> or an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nexed to the ſame, ſhall bee good and effectuall in Law, according to the purport and content of the ſaid Leaſes, againſt our ſaid Soueraigne Lord the Kings Maieſtie, his Heires and Succeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſors, and againſt all and euery perſon or perſons, that ſhall hereafter haue, inherite or enioy the ſaid Dukedome of <hi>Cornewall,</hi> by force of any Acte of Parliament, or other limitation whatſoeuer.</p>
            <p>Prouided alwayes, That euery ſuch Leaſe ſo to bee made, of any Mannors, Lands, Tene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, or Hereditaments in poſſeſſion, ſhall bee made but for three liues or fewer, or for one and thirty yeeres or vnder, or ſome other terme of yeeres determinable vpon one, two, or three liues, and not aboue. And if ſuch Leaſes be made in reuerſion, That then the ſame, together with the Eſtates in poſſeſſion, doe not exceede three liues, or the terme of one and thirty yeeres, and not in any wiſe diſpuniſhable of waſte: And ſo as vpon euery ſuch Leaſe ſhall be reſerued the ancient or moſt vſuall Rent, or ſuch Rent as hath beene yeelded or paid for the greater part of twenty yeeres next before the making of the ſaid Leaſes, and ſhall be reſerued due and payable, by, or to him or her that ſhall haue the inheritance or other Eſtate, of the ſaid Mannors, Lands, Tenements, or Hereditaments. And where no ſuch Rent hath beene reſerued or payable, that then, vpon euery ſuch Leaſe, there ſhall be reſerued a reaſonable Rent, not being vnder the twentieth part of the cleare yeerely value of the Mannors, Lands, Tenements, or Hereditaments contained in ſuch Leaſe.</p>
            <p>And be it further ordained and enacted by authority of this preſent Parliament, That all Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenants, Conditions, and Reſeruations, and other agreements contained in euery Leaſe ſo to be made, as aforeſaid, ſhall be good and effectuall in Law, according to the words and contents of the ſame, aſwell for, and againſt them, to whom the Reuerſion of the ſame Mannors, Lands, Tenements, or Hereditaments ſhall come, as for and againſt them to whom the ſaid Leaſes ſhall come, reſpectiuely: As if our ſaid Soueraigne Lord the Kings Maieſty at the time of the making of ſuch Couenants, Conditions, and Reſeruations, and other agreements were ſeized of an ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolute and indefeizible eſtate in Fee ſimple, in the ſame Mannors, Lands, Tenements, or Heredi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taments: Sauing alwayes to all and euery perſon and perſons, bodies Politique and Corpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate, their Heires and Succeſſors, Executors, Adminiſtrators, and Aſſignes, (other then our ſaid Soueraigne Lord the Kings Maieſty and his Heires, and all and euery perſon and perſons that ſhall hereafter haue, inherite, or enioy the ſaid Dukedome of <hi>Cornewall,</hi> by force of any Acte of Parliament, or other limitation whatſoeuer) all ſuch Rights, Titles, Eſtates, Cuſtomes, Inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſts, Termes, Claimes, and Demands whatſoeuer, of what kinde, nature, or quality whatſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer, of, in, to, or out of the ſaid Mannors, Lands, Tenements, or Hereditaments, or any of them, as they or any of them had, or ought to haue had before the making of this Acte, to all intents and purpoſes, and in as large and ample manner and forme, as if this Acte had neuer beene had or made: This Acte or any thing therein contained to the contrary notwithſtanding.</p>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="colophon">
            <p>
               <g ref="char:leaf">❧</g> Imprinted at London by BONHAM NORTON and IOHN BILL, Printers to the Kings moſt Excellent Maieſtie. M.DC.XXVI.</p>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
